<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://autismwinnipeg.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://autismwinnipeg.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-01-28T15:08:53+03:00</updated><id>https://autismwinnipeg.com/</id><title type="html">Autism Winnipeg</title><subtitle>Autism conferances in US UK and Winnipeg</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Who is affected by Autism?</title><link href="https://autismwinnipeg.com/who" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who is affected by Autism?" /><published>2017-05-30T20:23:13+03:00</published><updated>2017-05-30T20:23:13+03:00</updated><id>https://autismwinnipeg.com/who</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://autismwinnipeg.com/who">&lt;p&gt;Autism is one of the most common developmental disabilities. Individuals are of all races and ethnic and socioeconomic backgrounds. Current estimates suggest that approximately 400,000 individuals in the United States have autism. Autism is three to four times more likely to affect boys than girls. Autism occurs in individuals of all levels of intelligence. Approximately 75 percent are of low intelligence while 10 percent may demonstrate high intelligence in specific areas such as math.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Autism is one of the most common developmental disabilities. Individuals are of all races and ethnic and socioeconomic backgrounds. Current estimates suggest that approximately 400,000 individuals in the United States have autism. Autism is three to four times more likely to affect boys than girls. Autism occurs in individuals of all levels of intelligence. Approximately 75 percent are of low intelligence while 10 percent may demonstrate high intelligence in specific areas such as math.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Autism?</title><link href="https://autismwinnipeg.com/what" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Autism?" /><published>2017-05-28T20:23:13+03:00</published><updated>2017-05-28T20:23:13+03:00</updated><id>https://autismwinnipeg.com/what</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://autismwinnipeg.com/what">&lt;p&gt;Autism and the autism spectrum disorders are more common in the pediatric population than are some better known disorders such as diabetes, spinal bifida, or Down syndrome. Prevalence studies have been done in several states and also in the United Kingdom, Europe, and Asia. Prevalence estimates range from 2 to 6 per 1,000 children. This wide range of prevalence points to a need for earlier and more accurate screening for the symptoms of ASD. The earlier the disorder is diagnosed, the sooner the child can be helped through treatment interventions. Pediatricians, family physicians, daycare providers, teachers, and parents may initially dismiss signs of ASD, optimistically thinking the child is just a little slow and will “catch up.” Although early intervention has a dramatic impact on reducing symptoms and increasing a child’s ability to grow and learn new skills, it is estimated that only 50 percent of children are diagnosed before kindergarten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All children with ASD demonstrate deficits in 1) social interaction, 2) verbal and nonverbal communication, and 3) repetitive behaviors or interests. In addition, they will often have unusual responses to sensory experiences, such as certain sounds or the way objects look. Each of these symptoms runs the gamut from mild to severe. They will present in each individual child differently. For instance, a child may have little trouble learning to read but exhibit extremely poor social interaction. Each child will display communication, social, and behavioral patterns that are individual but fit into the overall diagnosis of ASD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Autism and the autism spectrum disorders are more common in the pediatric population than are some better known disorders such as diabetes, spinal bifida, or Down syndrome. Prevalence studies have been done in several states and also in the United Kingdom, Europe, and Asia. Prevalence estimates range from 2 to 6 per 1,000 children. This wide range of prevalence points to a need for earlier and more accurate screening for the symptoms of ASD. The earlier the disorder is diagnosed, the sooner the child can be helped through treatment interventions. Pediatricians, family physicians, daycare providers, teachers, and parents may initially dismiss signs of ASD, optimistically thinking the child is just a little slow and will “catch up.” Although early intervention has a dramatic impact on reducing symptoms and increasing a child’s ability to grow and learn new skills, it is estimated that only 50 percent of children are diagnosed before kindergarten.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Launch the First Ever Autism Conference</title><link href="https://autismwinnipeg.com/tony_blair" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Launch the First Ever Autism Conference" /><published>2017-05-26T20:23:13+03:00</published><updated>2017-05-26T20:23:13+03:00</updated><id>https://autismwinnipeg.com/tony_blair</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://autismwinnipeg.com/tony_blair">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tony Blair,&lt;/strong&gt; thoughts on autism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister, United Kingdom&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to launch the first ever internet conference on a disability issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I congratulate the National Autistic Society for having taken this initiative and for all the work they do with adults and children with autistic sprectrum disorder. The autism websites can help develop our understanding of what is a very very difficult issue. Autism is often a very hidden disability. Communication about it’s nature is very difficult when autism itself involves a difficulty in interacting with other people. Families find it very difficult to cope with. People find it very difficult to come to terms with. Often when we’re dealing with children or adults with autism we see people that appear to be in every respect fully able bodied and yet as a result of autism there is one of the most fundamental problems they have to cope with, namely the inability to communicate and interact with other people in a normal way. So, it’s a difficult problem and it’s one which we’re only just beginning to understand the full implications of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the autism websites is to help parents and families, but also health and education professionals to exchange information, pool ideas, to get to know how different people are coping with this problem and indeed how different countries are. In Britain there are around half a million people with autism, in the world there are some forty million worldwide. The autism websites is a significant and important step in trying to help teach us more about this disability, more about how we cope with it and more about how we help each other to understand all the problems that autism gives rise to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I welcome the initiative very much indeed, I think it’s taken a lot of vision and imagination by the National Autistic Society to launch it, and I know that it will offer a lot of comfort and real help to thousands possibly millions of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Tony Blair, thoughts on autism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What are the Autism Spectrum Disorders?</title><link href="https://autismwinnipeg.com/spectrum" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What are the Autism Spectrum Disorders?" /><published>2017-05-24T20:23:13+03:00</published><updated>2017-05-24T20:23:13+03:00</updated><id>https://autismwinnipeg.com/spectrum</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://autismwinnipeg.com/spectrum">&lt;h2 id=&quot;spectrum-disorders&quot;&gt;Spectrum Disorders&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not until the middle of the twentieth century was there a name for a disorder that now appears to affect an estimated one of every five hundred children, a disorder that causes disruption in families and unfulfilled lives for many children. In 1943 Dr. Leo Kanner of the Johns Hopkins Hospital studied a group of 11 children and introduced the label early infantile autism into the English language. At the same time a German scientist, Dr. Hans Asperger, described a milder form of the disorder that became known as Asperger syndrome. Thus these two disorders were described and are today listed in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders DSM-IV-TR (fourth edition, text revision) 1 as two of the five pervasive developmental disorders (PDD), more often referred to today as autism spectrum disorders (ASD). All these disorders are characterized by varying degrees of impairment in communication skills, social interactions, and restricted, repetitive and stereotyped patterns of behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Spectrum Disorders</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Research findings are relevant to Autism?</title><link href="https://autismwinnipeg.com/research" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Research findings are relevant to Autism?" /><published>2017-05-22T20:23:13+03:00</published><updated>2017-05-22T20:23:13+03:00</updated><id>https://autismwinnipeg.com/research</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://autismwinnipeg.com/research">&lt;p&gt;Research into the causes, the diagnosis, and the treatment of autism spectrum disorders has advanced in tandem. With new well-researched standardized diagnostic tools, ASD can be diagnosed at an early age. And with early diagnosis, the treatments found to be beneficial in recent years can be used to help the child with ASD develop to his or her greatest potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past few years, there has been public interest in a theory that suggested a link between the use of thimerosal, a mercury-based preservative used in the measles-mumps-rubella (MMR) vaccine, and autism. Although mercury is no longer found in childhood vaccines in the United States, some parents still have concerns about vaccinations. Many well-done, large-scale studies have now been done that have failed to show a link between thimerosal and autism. A panel from the Institute of Medicine is now examining these studies, including a large Danish study that concluded that there was no causal relationship between childhood vaccination using thimerosal-containing vaccines and the development of an autism spectrum disorder, 27 and a U.S. study looking at exposure to mercury, lead, and other heavy metals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Research into the causes, the diagnosis, and the treatment of autism spectrum disorders has advanced in tandem. With new well-researched standardized diagnostic tools, ASD can be diagnosed at an early age. And with early diagnosis, the treatments found to be beneficial in recent years can be used to help the child with ASD develop to his or her greatest potential.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">About Autism with Dr. Oliver Sacks</title><link href="https://autismwinnipeg.com/oliver_sacks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="About Autism with Dr. Oliver Sacks" /><published>2017-05-20T20:23:13+03:00</published><updated>2017-05-20T20:23:13+03:00</updated><id>https://autismwinnipeg.com/oliver_sacks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://autismwinnipeg.com/oliver_sacks">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q:  Welcome Dr Sacks to the Internet Conference.  You’re very well known through your work in the field of neurology and also with the public through your books, two of which, films have been based upon.  ‘At First Sight’ and ‘Awakenings’.  For those who may not yet have heard about you, could you say who you are and a little of your background?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OLIVER SACKS:  Well, I’m Oliver Sacks and I’m a Londoner.  I was born in London in 1933 and came to the States in 1960 and I’ve been here ever since. I was drawn to Neurology very early I think it was partly because my Parents were trained in neurology and in 1966 I encountered the astonishing patients whom I wrote about and later depicted in Awakenings. I think I’ve always been interested in extreme conditions, which challenge people’s resilience and humanity and, in a sense, force them to create a life and an identity upon an unusual basis. It is certainly one of the things, which has brought me to see people with Tourette’s syndrome, with autism, among some other conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yes, much of your work has been about uncovering the mysterious.  How far can we go in understanding the many complex interactions that make up the human brain?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a big question.  The human brain and mind are unimaginably complex and until recently, I think there was little understanding of phenomena much above the reflex level.  Now we are sort of looking at things like visual perception - now there’s something like 40 or 50 different systems say, which are involved in analysing colour, orientation, depth, movement all sorts of other parameters with visual perception.  The image on the retina is just the beginning of all this.  What is so difficult to understand, is how these 40 or 50 different systems are all orchestrated together seamlessly, to give us our picture of the world.  We see the world as coloured, moving, significant, interesting, our attention darts around and we are really very ignorant at this point of the nature of consciousness and attention and what sort of brain processes could possibly be involved. But it would certainly involve the synchronisation of many, many systems in all parts of the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Autism is still a puzzling disorder, with theories ranging from differences in brain composition and development to auto-immune theories.  How do you view the different strands of research?  Will there be a single unifying cause discovered, or do you think that autism manifests in different ways and has a number of sub-groups?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, as start, prior to 1960 on the whole autism was not seen as an organic condition at all.  And certainly, Bettleheim and others had thought that it was a consequence of bad parenting, in particular, sort of cold, refrigerator mothers.  I think that a whole generation of parents was made to feel guilty and uncomfortable because of this.  It was only in the 1960’s, that the feeling changed somewhat.  This was partly because of the german measles epidemic at that time, and it was found that the children of mothers who had had german measles in the first semester, could have various forms of brain damage and could be blind or deaf or retarded or autistic or all of the above.  This very strongly suggested a biological origin for autism.  Obviously, whatever biological determinants are there, these will then interact with all sorts of human determinants.  A mother’s responses to her child will partly be based on the way the child reacts; the interplay has to start on the first day of life.  And it may be that the interaction with an autistic child goes wrong or is peculiar from the first day of life. This has certainly been suggested, even though autism is usually only recognised in the second year of life.  There are more and more suggestions that there is something there in the first year of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right from the start, somewhat different forms or manifestations of autism were described, in fact at exactly the same time with Kanner and Asperger, Kanner describing a form of infantile autism in which those effected, really never achieved very good language and might be imprisoned in stereotypies … it is interesting that both Kanner and Asperger, in different countries, provided descriptions which are so similar in a way and both of them converged on the word autism to deliver the essential aloneness.  Autism had previously been used as a word in relation to schizophrenia, as a manifestation of schizophrenia.  It was not suggested that the infantile autism which Kanner described was a form of schizophrenia, yet there was this aloneness.  Although it was felt by both of them that the aloneness was not on the basis of fear or defense or withdrawal, but on the basis of some incapacity to understand other’s feelings, to express their own feelings and to know where they stood in a world of feeling. In the patients who Kanner described, language was never adequately achieved and people tended to remain fairly disabled. In the form that Asperger described, language and high intelligence were certainly possible but it might be a very different sort of life.  But whether the Kanner form and the Asperger form are separate conditions or whether they are parts of a continuum, one doesn’t know.  I have the impression of what we call autism, is very heterogeneous, both in its origin and its evolvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There appears to be a growing incidence of autism in many countries, with huge percentage increases being noted over the last 10 years in the USA.  What is your belief on this increase?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know whether it’s a fair comparison, but I would think of the supposed increase in say Tourette’s syndrome as a parallel.  In 1970 or the late 60’s for example, it was considered that Tourette’s syndrome was very rare, with the incidence of perhaps one in a million after seeing a patient with Tourette’s myself, on the streets of New York, and then seeing three more the next day and two more the day after, I wondered if I’d been somehow not seeing these people. And I thought I’ve seen five people in two days, this must be a thousand times commoner.  We now realise that Tourette’s is a thousand times commoner, it’s incidence, roughly speaking is one in a thousand not one in a million.  It has not become commoner, we’ve simply become more aware of it.  I would suspect something of the sort may be the case with autism.  Perhaps it wasn’t recognised or not talked about. Twenty-five years ago, when I was working in a state hospital in New York, people with autism were not clearly differentiated from people with retardation or people with schizophrenia or other conditions.  I think it’s probably our clearer perception of what constitutes autism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’ve actually worked with very many able individuals with autism, why do you think that different therapies, for example art therapy and music therapy have such different effects on people with autism?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, people with autism, despite their autism or in addition to their autism or beyond their autism, are as various as any other people.  Music perhaps, will affect some people and not affect others.  Some people with autism are visually gifted, and not others.  Some are mathematically gifted and not others.  I think one has to find the area which stimulates and excites them.  I think that the right therapy, which might become the right occupation for someone with autism as with any of us, depends on their particular interests or abilities.  For example I’m in a rather botanical mood at the moment, I’m wearing a Kew Gardens T-shirt and I know that at one time at least, Kew Gardens employed two or three young autistic people who had a talent and a love for botanical drawing. So botanical drawing was for them a therapy, a vocation, a satisfaction or whatever. A skill doesn’t always correspond to a feeling.  I know you’ve interviewed Temple Grandin, I’m not sure whether I should say this or not, she may have said it herself, Temple is very musical in a sense, she has a very good musical memory, a very good, clear grasp of musical form, she has absolute pitch, she is intrigued by music, but I don’t know if it arouses much feeling for her.  One Christmas she was here, and told me that she would be at a concert.  A Bach concert, where two of a three part inventions… would be played. She wondered if Bach could have written any four or five part inventions.  That was an interesting question and I said “Did you enjoy the concert?” and she said she found him very, very ingenious, but she wasn’t sure if she’d enjoyed it. Now this being so, I’m not sure that music would be therapeutic for Temple.  It may sort of challenge her, but it doesn’t please her much, whereas clearly being with animals and being in touch with their feelings and the way they think, is vitally important for her.  It becomes both her therapy and her profession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you think there are advantages for people with autism and Asperger syndrome in being alienated from their emotions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there are certain strengths which can go with the autistic syndromes which can confer advantage.  I think autistic people may have a great power of focusing which can show itself from an early age.  They tend to develop very intense passions, sometimes called obsessions, but I don’t feel one has to use a pathologising word like this.  Whether the passion has to do with astronomy, or as with Sherlock Holmes who was perhaps autistic, identifying the ash from 145 different sorts of cigar.  This intense focused interest can be a real strength.  I think that the relative absence of emotional involvement may sometimes be an advantage.  Temple, again, feels that she can be a particularly good umpire of scientific papers, as she feels she has no particular axes to grind, no biases and no prejudices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I can try and answer your question, by reference to a very great scientist, namely Cavendish who lived in the 18th century.  Cavendish weighed the earth, he discovered the composition of water, he was the first to make hydrogen - a major, major figure.  The Cavendish Laboratories in Cambridge, are named after him, but he was a very unusual man.  I’ve got here, part of an 1850-ish biography of Cavendish.  I’m going to read a little bit to you, because I think he sounds like an example of an autistic genius:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“He did not love, he did not hate, he did not hope, he did not fear, he did not worship as others do.  He was almost passionless, all that was needed for application more than the pure intellect and that would require the exercise of fancy imagination, affection or faith was distasteful to Cavendish.  An intellectual head, thinking.  A pair of wonderfully acute eyes, observing and a pair of very skillful hands, experimenting or recording are all that I realise in reading his memorials.  His brain seems to have been but a calculating engine, his eyes inlets of vision not fountains of tears.  His hands, instruments of manipulation which never trembled with emotion.  His heart, only an anatomical organ necessary for the circulation of the blood.  He is more to be wondered at, than blamed.  Cavendish did not stand aloof from other men in a proud or supercilious spirit refusing to count from his fellows. He felt himself separated from them by a great gulf which neither they, nor he could bridge over and across which it was vain to stretch hands or exchange greetings.  He was like a deaf mute, sitting apart from a circle, whose looks and gestures show that they utterly listening to music and eloquence … Wisely, therefore, he dwelt apart and bidding the world farewell took the self-imposed views of a scientific anchorite, and like the monks of old, shut himself up within his cell which was a kingdom sufficient for him and from its narrow window he saw as much of the universe as he cared to see.  He was one of the benefactors of his race.  He was patiently teaching and serving mankind whilst they were shrinking from his coldness or his peculiarities.  He was not a poet, a priest or a prophet.  Only a cold clear intelligence laying down pure, white light which brightened everything on which it fell but warmed nothing. A star of at least the second, if not of the first magnitude in the intellectual firmament.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve never seen this quote, and this is a very rare book for my office, a biography.  But, there’s much more of the same, I have one very, very astounding picture.  The biographer, who was a physician, wonders whether this was an innate disposition of Cavendish or whether it was due to early bereavement, his mother died when he was two and he was probably brought up by a rather absentee father.  But it’s that sort of remarkable strength or efficiencies that are combined here - so in answer to your question, this is it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’ve written two books which include cases of your clients on the autistic spectrum.  The man who mistook his wife for a hat and an anthropologist on Mars.  In these books you describe their worlds in great detail enabling the reader to gain some kind of understanding of what it must be like.  Do you think that people who are neurologically typical, should be more aware of the needs of those with autism and change their behaviour to accommodate those needs.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, I’m not quite sure what typical or normal means, and I think there are a great many modes of being human which can be rich and full, even though they are very different.  This is often brought up by deaf people, who in fact like to distinguish deaf with a small ‘d’ which means hearing-impaired from deaf with a large ‘D’ which means really belonging to an ethnic group, a linguistic and cultural group, which has its own perspective, sensibilities, community, culture, language. So that deaf people, especially if they are native signers and are part of the deaf community, do not feel defective or pathological, but they feel different.  They also feel that they are complete in themselves.  I think autistic people, especially gifted autistic people, may sometimes feel the same.  Temple herself would say “if I could snap my fingers and be non-autistic, I wouldn’t, because autism and being autistic is part of the way I am”.  Now with Cavendish, whom I spoke of, it was very well recognised by his contemporaries, that they had to adapt to him.  For example, he could not bear being looked at directly, he couldn’t bear being talked to directly, if they turned to him, of course he might feel on him, with a question, he would shrink away.  It was understood very well that one had to give an animated conversation with someone else, but if a subject interested Cavendish, he would then be drawn towards the conversation and come into it.  Cavendish couldn’t bear society, he could only sometimes bear interactions with a single person.  One has to be sensitive with everyone, you have to adapt to everyone.  All human relationships are about mutual adaptation and I don’t know how conscious this is, I think empathy teaches one to adapt.  I think adaptation is very important.  But certainly with autistic people, one is dealing with, in a sense, another variety or another species of human being.  They may be very intelligent and very sensitive and very valid in their own way, and yet it may be a different way.  I think we do have to adapt somewhat, as they do.  It was said long ago by Diderot of the 18th century that the problem for blind people is not being blind, it’s not seeing people. In other words, they have to adapt to the seeing world.  Certainly for people who are totally colour blind, of whom I’ve seen a good many, the problem is having to learn a vocabulary of colour, that which means absolutely nothing to them.  They could get along perfectly well without it.  To some extent, autistic people have to learn the vocabulary of what it’s like to be us. I think we also have to learn their vocabulary and I think best way to learn about deaf people is to have a deaf neighbour, deaf friend or deaf relative.  Similarly, the best way to learn about autism is to find yourself in some sort of relationship with an autistic person. I will say that I think I have some autistic colleagues, whether they would think I’m one of their autistic colleagues or not I don’t know. Yes, one adapts all the while.  Hopefully&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Well Dr Sacks, thank you very much.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Q: Welcome Dr Sacks to the Internet Conference. You’re very well known through your work in the field of neurology and also with the public through your books, two of which, films have been based upon. ‘At First Sight’ and ‘Awakenings’. For those who may not yet have heard about you, could you say who you are and a little of your background?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Medications are used with Autism?</title><link href="https://autismwinnipeg.com/meds" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Medications are used with Autism?" /><published>2017-05-16T20:23:13+03:00</published><updated>2017-05-16T20:23:13+03:00</updated><id>https://autismwinnipeg.com/meds</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://autismwinnipeg.com/meds">&lt;p&gt;Medications for autism are often used to treat behavioral problems, such as aggression, self-injurious behavior, and severe tantrums, that keep the person with ASD from functioning more effectively at home or school. The medications used are those that have been developed to treat similar symptoms in other disorders. Many of these medications are prescribed “off-label.” This means they have not been officially approved by the FDA for use in children, but the doctor prescribes the medications if he or she feels they are appropriate for your child. You may discover that these medications are antidepressants or anti-seizure medications if you look them up.  Further research needs to be done to ensure not only the efficacy but the safety of psychotropic agents used in the treatment of children and adolescents.  Some antidepressants are no longer recommended in children, for example.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Medications for autism are often used to treat behavioral problems, such as aggression, self-injurious behavior, and severe tantrums, that keep the person with ASD from functioning more effectively at home or school. The medications used are those that have been developed to treat similar symptoms in other disorders. Many of these medications are prescribed “off-label.” This means they have not been officially approved by the FDA for use in children, but the doctor prescribes the medications if he or she feels they are appropriate for your child. You may discover that these medications are antidepressants or anti-seizure medications if you look them up. Further research needs to be done to ensure not only the efficacy but the safety of psychotropic agents used in the treatment of children and adolescents. Some antidepressants are no longer recommended in children, for example.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Autism</title><link href="https://autismwinnipeg.com/index-page" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Autism" /><published>2017-05-14T20:23:13+03:00</published><updated>2017-05-14T20:23:13+03:00</updated><id>https://autismwinnipeg.com/index</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://autismwinnipeg.com/index-page">&lt;p&gt;The brain disorder autism begins in early childhood and persists throughout adulthood affecting three crucial areas of development: verbal and nonverbal communication, social interaction, and creative or imaginative play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Autism is the most common of a group of conditions called pervasive developmental disorders (PDDs). PDDs involve delays in many areas of childhood development. The first signs of autism are usually noticed by the age of three. Many individuals who are autistic also develop epilepsy, a brain disorder that causes convulsive seizures, as they approach adulthood. Other characteristics may include repetitive and ritualistic behaviors, hand flapping, spinning or running in circles, excessive fears, self-injury such as head banging or biting, aggression, insensitivity to pain, temper tantrums, and sleeping and eating disturbances. Autistic individuals live a normal life span, but most require lifelong care and supervision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leo Kanner first identified autism in 1943 when he described 11 self-absorbed children who had “autistic disturbances of affect contact.” At first, autism was thought to be an attachment disorder resulting from poor parenting. This has been proved to be a myth. While the cause remains a mystery, most specialists now view autism as a brain disorder that makes it difficult for the person to process and respond to the world. Autism has been observed in several members of the same families. Therefore, many scientists believe that, at least in some individuals, autism may be genetic. Scientists have identified some genes as playing a possible role in the development of autism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some report that the Lindamood-Bell-Autism Learning Processes are helpful in treating persons with autism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The brain disorder autism begins in early childhood and persists throughout adulthood affecting three crucial areas of development: verbal and nonverbal communication, social interaction, and creative or imaginative play.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How is Autism Diagnosed?</title><link href="https://autismwinnipeg.com/how" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How is Autism Diagnosed?" /><published>2017-05-10T20:23:13+03:00</published><updated>2017-05-10T20:23:13+03:00</updated><id>https://autismwinnipeg.com/how</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://autismwinnipeg.com/how">&lt;p&gt;Although there are many concerns about labeling a young child with autism or an ASD, the earlier the diagnosis of ASD is made, the earlier needed interventions can begin. Evidence over the last 15 years indicates that intensive early intervention in optimal educational settings for at least 2 years during the preschool years results in improved outcomes in most young children with ASD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In evaluating a child who might have autism, clinicians rely on behavioral characteristics to make a diagnosis. Some of the characteristic behaviors of ASD may be apparent in the first few months of a child’s life, or they may appear at any time during the early years. For the diagnosis, problems in at least one of the areas of communication, socialization, or restricted behavior must be present before the age of 3. The diagnosis requires a two-stage process. The first stage involves developmental screening during “well child” check-ups; the second stage entails a comprehensive evaluation by a multidisciplinary team.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Although there are many concerns about labeling a young child with autism or an ASD, the earlier the diagnosis of ASD is made, the earlier needed interventions can begin. Evidence over the last 15 years indicates that intensive early intervention in optimal educational settings for at least 2 years during the preschool years results in improved outcomes in most young children with ASD.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Research into Causes and Treatment of Autism Spectrum Disorders</title><link href="https://autismwinnipeg.com/autism5" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Research into Causes and Treatment of Autism Spectrum Disorders" /><published>2017-05-08T20:23:13+03:00</published><updated>2017-05-08T20:23:13+03:00</updated><id>https://autismwinnipeg.com/autism5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://autismwinnipeg.com/autism5">&lt;p&gt;Research into the causes, the diagnosis, and the treatment of autism
spectrum disorders has advanced in tandem. With new well-researched
standardized diagnostic tools, ASD can be diagnosed at an early age. And
with early diagnosis, the treatments found to be beneficial in recent
years can be used to help the child with ASD develop to his or her
greatest potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past few years, there has been public interest in a theory that
suggested a link between the use of thimerosal, a mercury-based
preservative used in the measles-mumps-rubella (MMR) vaccine, and
autism. Although mercury is no longer found in childhood vaccines in the
United States, some parents still have concerns about vaccinations. Many
well-done, large-scale studies have now been done that have failed to
show a link between thimerosal and autism. A panel from the Institute of
Medicine is now examining these studies, including a large Danish study
that concluded that there was no causal relationship between childhood
vaccination using thimerosal-containing vaccines and the development of
an autism spectrum disorder, 27 and a U.S. study looking at exposure to
mercury, lead, and other heavy metals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research on the Biologic Basis of ASD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://rcm-images.amazon.com/images/G/01/rcm/468x336.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Shop at
Amazon.com&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of its relative inaccessibility, scientists have only recently
been able to study the brain systematically. But with the emergence of
new brain imaging tools-computerized tomography (CT), positron emission
tomography (PET), single photon emission computed tomography (SPECT),
and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), study of the structure and the
functioning of the brain can be done. With the aid of modern technology
and the new availability of both normal and autism tissue samples to do
postmortem studies, researchers will be able to learn much through
comparative studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Postmortem and MRI studies have shown that many major brain structures
are implicated in autism. This includes the cerebellum, cerebral cortex,
limbic system, corpus callosum, basal ganglia, and brain stem. 28 Other
research is focusing on the role of neurotransmitters such as serotonin,
dopamine, and epinephrine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Image of major brain structures implicated in autism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research into the causes of autism spectrum disorders is being fueled by
other recent developments. Evidence points to genetic factors playing a
prominent role in the causes for ASD. Twin and family studies have
suggested an underlying genetic vulnerability to ASD. 29 To further
research in this field, the Autism Genetic Resource Exchange, a project
initiated by the Cure Autism Now Foundation, and aided by an NIMH grant,
is recruiting genetic samples from several hundred families. Each family
with more than one member diagnosed with ASD is given a 2-hour, in-home
screening. With a large number of DNA samples, it is hoped that the most
important genes will be found. This will enable scientists to learn what
the culprit genes do and how they can go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another exciting development is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.brainbank.org&quot;&gt;Autism Tissue
Program&lt;/a&gt;, supported by the Autism Society of
America Foundation, the Medical Investigation of Neurodevelopmental
Disorders (M.I.N.D.) Institute at the University of California, Davis,
and the National Alliance for Autism Research. The program is aided by a
grant to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.brainbank.mclean.org&quot;&gt;Harvard Brain and Tissue Resource
Center&lt;/a&gt;, funded by the National
Institute of Mental Health (NIMH) and the National Institute of
Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS). Studies of the postmortem
brain with imaging methods will help us learn why some brains are large,
how the limbic system develops, and how the brain changes as it ages.
Tissue samples can be stained and will show which neurotransmitters are
being made in the cells and how they are transported and released to
other cells. By focusing on specific brain regions and
neurotransmitters, it will become easier to identify susceptibility
genes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recent neuroimaging studies have shown that a contributing cause for
autism may be abnormal brain development beginning in the infant’s first
months.&lt;/strong&gt; This “growth dysregulation hypothesis” holds that the
anatomical abnormalities seen in autism are caused by genetic defects in
brain growth factors. It is possible that sudden, rapid head growth in
an infant may be an early warning signal that will lead to early
diagnosis and effective biological intervention or possible prevention
of autism. 30&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For detailed information on autism spectrum disorders research, see NIMH
research fact sheet, Autism Spectrum Disorders Research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Children’s Health Act of 2000-What It Means to Autism Research&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Children’s Health Act of 2000 was responsible for the creation of
the Interagency Autism Coordinating Committee (IACC), a committee that
includes the directors of five NIH institutes-the National Institute of
Mental Health, the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and
Stroke, the National Institute on Deafness and Other Communication
Disorders (NIDCD), the National Institute of Child Health and Human
Development (NICHD), and the National Institute of Environmental Health
Sciences (NIEHS)-as well as representatives from the Health Resource
Services Administration, the National Center on Birth Defects and
Developmental Disabilities (a part of the Centers for Disease Control),
the Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry, the Substance
Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration, the Administration on
Developmental Disabilities, the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid
Services, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration, and the U.S. Department
of Education. The Committee, instructed by the Congress to develop a
10-year agenda for autism research, introduced the plan, dubbed a
“matrix” or a “roadmap,” at the first Autism Summit Conference in
November 2003. The roadmap indicates priorities for research for years 1
to 3, years 4 to 6, and years 7 to 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The five NIH institutes of the IACC have established the Studies to
Advance Autism Research and Treatment (STAART) Network, composed of
eight network centers. They will conduct research in the fields of
developmental neurobiology, genetics, and psychopharmacology. Each
center is pursuing its own particular mix of studies, but there also
will be multi-site clinical trials within the STAART network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The STAART centers are located at the following sites:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yale University, Connecticut&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;University of Washington, Seattle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;University of California, Los Angeles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mount Sinai Medical School, New York&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kennedy Krieger Institute, Maryland&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Boston University, Massachusetts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;University of Rochester, New York&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A data coordination center will analyze the data generated by both the
STAART network and the Collaborative Programs of Excellence in Autism
(CPEA). This latter program, funded by the NICHD and the NIDCD Network
on the Neurobiology and Genetics of Autism, consists of 10 sites. The
CPEA is at present studying the world’s largest group of well-diagnosed
individuals with autism characterized by genetic and developmental
profiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The CPEA centers are located at:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Boston University, Massachusetts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;University of California, Davis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;University of California, Irvine&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;University of California, Los Angeles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yale University, Connecticut&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;University of Washington, Seattle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;University of Rochester, New York&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;University of Texas, Houston&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;University of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;University of Utah, Salt Lake City&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NIEHS has programs at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Center for Childhood Neurotoxicology and Assessment, University of
Medicine &amp;amp; Dentistry, New Jersey * The Center for the Study of
Environmental Factors in the Etiology of Autism, University of
California, Davis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 American Psychiatric Association. Diagnostic and statistical manual of
mental disorders: DSM-IV-TR (fourth edition, text revision). Washington
DC: American Psychiatric Association, 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 Filipek PA, Accardo PJ, Baranek GT, Cook Jr. EH, Dawson G, Gordon B,
Gravel JS, Johnson CP, Kellen RJ, Levy SE, Minshew NJ, Prizant BM, Rapin
I, Rogers SJ, Stone WL, Teplin S, Tuchman RF, Volkmar FR. The screening
and diagnosis of autism spectrum disorders. Journal of Autism and
Developmental Disorders, 1999; 29(2): 439-484.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 Newschaffer CJ (Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health).
Autism Among Us: Rising Concerns and the Public Health Response [Video
on the Internet]. Public Health Training Network, 2003 June 20.
Available from:
http://www.publichealthgrandrounds.unc.edu/autism/webcast.htm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4 Volkmar FR. Medical Problems, Treatments, and Professionals. In:
Powers MD, ed. Children with Autism: A Parent’s Guide, Second Edition.
Bethesda, MD: Woodbine House, 2000; 73-74.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5 Powers MD. What Is Autism? In: Powers MD, ed. Children with Autism: A
Parent’s Guide, Second Edition. Bethesda, MD: Woodbine House, 2000, 28.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6 Smalley SI, Autism and tuberous sclerosis. Journal of Autism and
Developmental Disorders, 1998; 28(5): 407-414.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7 Filipek PA, Accardo PJ, Ashwal S, Baranek GT, Cook Jr. EH, Dawson G,
Gordon B, Gravel JS, Johnson CP, Kallen RJ, Levy SE, Minshew NJ, Ozonoff
S, Prizant BM, Rapin I, Rogers SJ, Stone WL, Teplin SW, Tuchman RF,
Volkmar FR. Practice parameter: screening and diagnosis of autism.
Neurology, 2000; 55: 468-479.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8 Baird G, Charman T, Baron-Cohen S, Cox A, Swettenham J, Wheelwright S,
Drew A. A screening instrument for autism at 18 months of age: A 6-year
follow-up study. Journal of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent
Psychiatry, 2000; 39: 694-702.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9 Robbins DI, Fein D, Barton MI, Green JA. The modified checklist for
autism in toddlers: an initial study investigating the early detection
of autism and pervasive developmental disorders. Journal of Autism and
Developmental Disorders, 2001; 31(2): 149-151.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10 Stone WL, Coonrod EE, Ousley OY. Brief report: screening tool for
autism in two-year-olds (STAT): development and preliminary data.
Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders, 2000; 30(6): 607-612.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11 Berument SK, Rutter M, Lord C, Pickles A, Bailey A. Autism Screening
Questionnaire: diagnostic validity. British Journal of Psychiatry, 1999;
175: 444-451.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12 Ehlers S, Gillberg C, Wing L. A screening questionnaire for Asperger
syndrome and other high-functioning autism spectrum disorders in school
age children. Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders, 1999;
29(2): 129-141.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13 Garnett MS, Attwood AJ. The Australian scale for Asperger’s syndrome.
In: Attwood, Tony. Asperger’s Syndrome: A Guide for Parents and
Professionals. London: Jessica Kingsley Publishers, 1997.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;14 Scott FJ, Baron-Cohen S, Bolton P, Brayne C. The Cast (Childhood
Asperger Syndrome Test): preliminary development of a UK screen for
mainstream primary-school-age children. Autism, 2002; 2(1): 9-31.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;15 Tadevosyan-Leyfer O, Dowd M, Mankoski R, Winklosky B, Putnam S,
McGrath L, Tager-Flusberg H, Folstein SE. A principal components
analysis of the autism diagnostic interview-revised. Journal of the
American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, 2003; 42(7):
864-872.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;16 Lord C, Risi S, Lambrecht L, Cook EH, Leventhal BL, DiLavore PC,
Pickles A, Rutter M. The autism diagnostic observation schedule-generic:
a standard measure of social and communication deficits associated with
the spectrum of autism. Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders,
2000; 30(3): 205-230.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;17 Van Bourgondien ME, Marcus LM, Schopler E. Comparison of DSM-III-R
and childhood autism rating scale diagnoses of autism. Journal of Autism
and Developmental Disorders, 1992; 22(4): 493-506.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;18 Department of Health and Human Services. Mental Health: A Report of
the Surgeon General. Rockville, MD: Department of Health and Human
Services, Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration,
Center for Mental Health Services, National Institute of Mental Health,
1999.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;19 Lovaas OI. Behavioral treatment and normal educational and
intellectual functioning in young autistic children. Journal of
Consulting and Clinical Psychology, 1987; 55: 3-9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;20 McEachin JJ, Smith T, Lovaas OI. Long-term outcome for children with
autism who received early intensive behavioral treatment. American
Journal on Mental Retardation, 1993; 97: 359-372.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;21 Couper JJ, Sampson AJ. Children with autism deserve evidence-based
intervention. Medical Journal of Australia, 2003; 178: 424-425.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;22 American Academy of Pediatrics Committee on Children With
Disabilities. The pediatrician’s role in the diagnosis and management of
autistic spectrum disorder in children. Pediatrics, 2001; 107(5):
1221-1226.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;23 Dunlap G, Foxe L. Teaching students with autism. ERIC EC Digest
#E582, 1999 October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;24 Autism Society of America. Biomedical and Dietary Treatments (Fact
Sheet) [cited 2004], 2003. Bethesda, MD: Autism Society of America.
Available from:
http://www.autism-society.org/site/PageServer?pagename=BiomedicalDietaryTrea
tments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;25 McDougle CJ, Stigler KA, Posey DJ. Treatment of aggression in
children and adolescents with autism and conduct disorder. Journal of
Clinical Psychiatry, 2003; 64 (supplement 4): 16-25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;26 Research Units on Pediatric Psychopharmacology Network. Risperidone
in children with autism and serious behavioral problems. New England
Journal of Medicine, 2002; 347(5): 314-321.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;27 Hviid A, Stellfeld M, Wohlfahrt J, Melbye M. Association between
thimerosal-containing vaccine and autism. JAMA, 2003; 290(13):
1763-1766.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;28 Akshoomoff N, Pierce K, Courchesne E. The neurobiological basis of
autism from a developmental perspective. Development and
Psychopathology, 2002; 14: 613-634.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;29 Korvatska E, Van de Water J, Anders TF, Gershwin ME. Genetic and
immunologic considerations in autism. Neurobiology of Disease, 2002; 9:
107-125.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;30 Courchesne E. Carper R, Akshoomoff N. Evidence of brain overgrowth in
the first year of life in autism. JAMA, 2003; 290(3): 337-344.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brochure was written by Margaret Strock, Office of Communications,
NIMH. Scientific information and review were provided by NIMH staff
members Stephen Foote, MD; Ann Wagner, PhD; Audrey Thurm, PhD; Benjamin
Vitiello, MD; Douglas Meinecke, PhD; and Judith Cooper, PhD, National
Institute on Deafness and Other Communication Disorders. Editorial
assistance was provided by Ruth Dubois and Antoinette Cooper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All material in this brochure is in the public domain and may be
reproduced or copied without permission from the Institute. Citation of
the National Institute of Mental Health as the source is appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NIH Publication No.04-5511 April 2004&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Citation for this publication:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strock, Margaret (2004). Autism Spectrum Disorders (Pervasive
Developmental Disorders). NIH Publication No. NIH-04-5511, National
Institute of Mental Health, National Institutes of Health, U.S.
Department of Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, 40 pp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../autism1.htm&quot;&gt;Back to Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Research into the causes, the diagnosis, and the treatment of autism spectrum disorders has advanced in tandem. With new well-researched standardized diagnostic tools, ASD can be diagnosed at an early age. And with early diagnosis, the treatments found to be beneficial in recent years can be used to help the child with ASD develop to his or her greatest potential.</summary></entry></feed>